Maine Acadian Cultural Survey Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 3: Graphic materials, The original materials are stored at Ft. Meade.
  - Black-and-white negatives, 3130 35mm black-white-film negatives
    - Native American Day, Grande Riviere Festival, Van Buren, Maine, July 15, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B045-4026; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document an event called Native American Day, held at the Village Acadien in Van Buren, ME, as part of the annual Grande Riviere Festival; 2-8, Pipe ceremony; event coordinator Guy Frigon (center, light-colored shirt) of Frenchville, ME, explains the ceremony to the spectators; 9-10, Singing and drumming begins for the first dance; 11-14, The dance begins; 15-22, The dance continues; spectators are asked to join the dance; 23-25, A second dance, similar to the first; Frigon said both dances were "circle dance"; 26-27, Handcarved wooden canoe containing the sweetgrass braid use in purification ritual (see MAP-DW-B044); 28-29, Frigon and another Mic-Mac, name unknown, demonstrate different drumming rhythms; 30-35, Visitors from the town of Ste-Ouenne, France, attended the event; here, the mayor of Ste-Ouenne tries on a headdress; 36-end, Field coordinator Ray Brassieur talks with one of event participants.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Van Buren, Maine, July 15, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B046-4021; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes; 1-5, St. Remi Catholic Church, village of Keegan, town of Van Buren, ME; the St. Remi parish was combined with the St. Bruno parish during the summer of 1991, and no services are currently held here; 6-7, Shrine in a yard in Keegan; these shrines are a common sight in the area; 8, Mike's Motors, Keegan; the facade on this garage is usually associated with commercial enterprises such as this, but many residential buildings in the study area also have facades; 9-11, Judy's Beauty Salon, Keegan; many area residents operate small businesses from their residences, and salons are especially common; 12-13, Wrought-iron roadside cross, a croix de chemin. Keegan; this one commemorates the site of an early Catholic church; 14-16, A house with a variety of lawn decorations, including a shrine; 17-18, Al's Neighborhood Store, Keegan; another commercial building with a facade, and another type of business/residence combination often found in the area; 19-20, Shed under construction in Van Buren; the gambrel style roof, locally called colm-casse, is found on a wide variety of buildings; 21, Partially-buried potato house, Hamlin, ME. The use of insulating earth-contact construction is an old and widespread technique; here it is used with a corrugated steel building of relatively recent vintage; 22-23, Spraying potato fields, Hamlin; area growers describe potato farming as input-intensive; 24, Trucks on a farm in Hamlin; many area farmers also do some type of trucking; 25, St. Joseph Catholic Church, Hamlin; 26, A small barn in Hamlin; 27, Buildings with facades on residential property in Hamlin; 28, Health care facility, Van Buren; a part of this facility is called L'Acadie; 29-30, Sign advertising buckwheat flour for sale in Van Buren; buckwheat flour is used to make ploves. a traditional Acadian food. No one was home, and I was unable to determine if the flour is actually sold here; 31, "Parking to see Indians" sign in a vacant lot across the road from the Village Acadien, where Native American Day had been held on the previous day; 32-33, An abandoned potato house by the railroad tracks in Van Buren; many of these warehouses, in which the produce was stored prior to shipment, are standing but no longer in use; 34, Sign at the Village Acadien in Van Buren; 35-36, A roadside cross, or croix de chemin. near the Village Acadien.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Van Buren, Maine, and Grand Isle, Maine, July 16, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B047-4025; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes; 2-3, Sign on a barn on the farm of Bert Sirois in Keegan village, town of Van Buren, ME; these custom-painted signs are found on most farms in the area; 4-5, A large L-shaped house in Keegan; this configuration, or variations of it, are a type found throughout the study area. Several presbyteries (e.g. Our Lady of Mount Carmel in Lille, ME) are built in this style; 6-7, House with lateral addition, Keegan; this is one of the most frequently found addition types; 8-10, Ste-Anne-de-Madawaska Catholic Church in New Brunswick, photographed from U.S. Highway 1; 11-12, Barn with double gambrel roof, Grand Isle, ME; this roof style, locally called colm-casse, is found on a variety of buildings, but this configuration is unusual; 13-14, House with lateral addition, Grand Isle; 15-16, A large L-shaped house in Grand Isle; 17-18, The Gun Hospital, Grand Isle; area residents operate a variety of businesses from their homes; 19-20, House with lateral addition, Grand Isle; 21-22, Catholic church in Grand Isle; 23-24, House with lateral addition, Grand Isle; 25-26, Shrine in a yard in Grand Isle; these shrines are found throughout the study area; 27-28, Shed with gambrel (colm-casse) roof, Grand Isle; 29-30, Large L-shaped house, Grand Isle; 31-32, House with lateral addition, Madawaska, ME; 33-34, Variation on L-shaped house configuration, Madawaska; this example has a gabled roof instead of the more commonly seen hipped roof; 35-36, Large L-shaped houses in Madawaska.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Upper St. John River Valley area, Maine, July 16, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B048-4024; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes; 1-2, Two small garages with facades in St. David village; such facades are usually associated with commercial properties, but in the study area a large number of structures on residential property have this feature; 3-4, Fred Albert house in St. David, a mid-nineteenth century house which has been moved to its present location on property owned by the Madawaska Historical Society and restored; 5, St. David Catholic Church; 6-7, This large elm tree was used by former railroad conductor Bob Labonte to mark the approach to Madawaska; 8-9, Looking across the bottomland of the St. John River valley in St. David, the Centre universitaire St-Louis-Maillet in Edmunston, New Brunswick, is visible in the distance; 10-11, Religious statuary, popular lawn ornaments in the study area, are sold at Bob's Neighborhood Store in Madawaska; 12-14, St. Thomas Aquinas Catholic Church, Madawaska; 15-16, Street sign at the corner of 5th and Evangeline Streets in Madawaska; Evangeline is the title heroine of Longfellow's poem about the Acadians; 17-19, Evangeline School in Madawaska; 20-21, Acadia School, Madawaska; 22-23, Sign in French bn a gas station in Madawaska; although nearly every adult in the study area speaks French, business signs in. French are not common in Maine; 24-25, Frenchville Starch Factory, Frenchville, ME, closed a few years ago; there is also an abandoned starch factory in Fort Kent, ME; 26-27, Sign on L. Dumais and Sons farm, Frenchville, ME; the picture of the truck and use of the term shipper typical, as many farmers are involved with trucking as well. Note the semi-trailer parked in front of the barn; 28, Trucks belonging to C. L. Roy and Sons, Frenchville; trucking by both farmers and independent operators is an important economic activity; 29-30, Sign on a barn on the farm of Edwin Pelletier and Sons, Frenchville, ME; 31-32, Parked across the street from the Pelletier barn is one of their trucks; 33-34, Classic Casuals, a clothing store in a home in Frenchville; many area residents operate small businesses at their homes; 35-36, St. Luce Catholic Church, Frenchville.
    - Various buildings and scenes; Ray Blair, independent logger, Fort Kent, Maine, July 17, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B049; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes; 2-7, Some of the buildings on Main St. in downtown Fort Kent, ME; Note: 8-13 were printed with the negative strip reversed; 8-9, Main St., downtown Fort Kent; 10-11, Rock's Motel on Main St.; 12-15, Sign marking the northern terminus of U.S. Highway 1; 16-17, Smart's Beauty Shop on Main St.; the number of beauty shops/salons in the study area seems large in proportion to the population; 18-24, Independent logger Ray Blair of Eagle Lake stacks logs he has cut from property on which he has purchased the timber-rights. Large-scale commercial logging has declined in importance in this part of the state, but a number of independent loggers still operate; 29-end, Logs are loaded onto a train car on Market St., in Fort Kent.
    - Danny Tardiff and Raoul Tardiff at their sawmill, Fort Kent, Maine, July 17, 1991 - July 18, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B050; David A. Whitman; 35 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      2-3, Logs are loaded onto a train car on Market St. in Fort Kent, ME; These images document a visit to the sawmill in Fort Kent owned and operated by Danny Tardiff. Danny bought the sawmill from his father Raoul in 1990. Raoul still works with Danny at the mill; 4, Blank frame; 5-7, Raoul Tardiff checks the board to see what the afternoon's work entails; 8, Danny Tardiff examines a piece of mill equipment; 9-11, Raoul, Danny, and mill employee John Plourde position a log to be fed into the main saw; 12-14, A log moves through the large circular saw; 15-17, Danny sometimes uses a chain was to finish cutting off pieces not entirely sawn through on the first pass; 18, Preparing for the next pass through the saw; each log goes through a number of times as it gets squared off and planks are sawn from it; 19-23, Raoul operates the large saw; 24-26, John Plourde helps turn the log before the next pass; 27-31, Raoul runs the saw; 32, Danny removes the pieces sawn off by the main saw; 33, Raoul; 34-end, Danny takes the large planks sawn off by the circular saw to a smaller saw and cuts them into boards of different widths.
    - Tardiff sawmill, Fort Kent, Maine; Brown's musical instruments, Wallagrass, Maine; Maps at Registry of Deeds, Fort Kent, Maine, July 18, 1991 - July 19, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B051; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document Tardiff sawmill in Fort Kent, ME; see MAP-DWB050 for more information; 2-3, Exterior view of the mill; 4-7, Logs and sawdust pile up outside the mill; 8, Saw sharpening device fabricated by Raoul Tardiff; these can be purchased commercially, but are expensive; 9, Spare parts, storage, and repair room in the mill; 10-12, Office; the object on the top of the desk is a windpowered model of loggers made by Raoul Tardiff. It is usually kept on a shelf in the office; 13, Planer, bought second-hand and refurbished by Raoul; 14-15, Danny Tardiff saws boards; 16-18, Spare parts, storage, and repair room; 19-20, Succession of mill ownership written in concrete at the door to the mill office. "Corriveau 1948" refers to the mill's builder, Joseph Corriveau. Raoul Tardiff bought the mill in 1961; These images document a collection of musical instruments which belonged to the late Theodore Brown of Wallagrass, ME. They are currently in the possession of his widow, Katherine; 21-22, An instrument called a "mandolin-guitar harp" by its manufacturer, The Home Educational Co. of Concord, North Carolina; the instrument has 4 6 strings; 23-24, Open-backed 5-string banjo made by S. S. Stewart, Philadelphia, PA. This banjo, as well as the two described below, are probably of late 1920s or early 1930s manufacture; 25-26, Long-necked Vega tenor banjo; 26-27, Another Vega tenor banjo, this one with the more usual shorter neck. Both Vega banjos had maple resonators and chrome tone rings; 29-30, Harmony tenor guitar, mahogany body and spruce top; vintage unknown. Tenor guitars enjoyed a brief surge in popularity during the "folk revival" of the 1960s, and this instrument may date from that period; These images document a series of maps photographed at the Registry of Deeds in Fort Kent, ME. Local historian Guy Dubay assisted me by finding relevant maps; 31-33, Madawaska; from an 1843 map by Philip Eastman, John W. Dana, and Henry M. Cunningham. Three tiers, or rang, of long lots can be seen extending back from the St. John River. This map contains the original site of the Fred Albert house, lot #138; 34-36, Van Buren; a composite map done in 1933 by Henry J. Pelletier using 1846 and 1860 maps. Notice how the long lots of the original grants given to the French meet the square plots granted later by the United States government. This area of later grants is often referred to as the concession; 37, Van Buren, from the Atlas of Aroostook County, Maine, by F. B. Roe and N. Geo. Colby, 1877. This map contains the sites of the house presently owned by Val Violette, and the Maison Heritage, a National Register of Historic Places house which is currently disassembled and under a tarp behind the house of Don Cyr in Lille, ME.
    - Maps and deeds at Registry of Deeds, Fort Kent, Maine; Musicians Paul-Emile Martin and Ida Roy performing, University of Maine-Fort Kent, Fort Kent, Maine, July 19, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B052; David A. Whitman; 38 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a series of maps and deeds photographed at the Registry of Deeds in Fort Kent, ME. See MAP-DW-B051 for more information; 0-11, Different views of the map of Van Buren from the 1877 Roe and Colby atlas; see MAP-DW-B051, #37 for more information; 12-17, Madawaska, from Roe and Colby; 18-23, Deed between Luc Albert and his father, Anselme; pertains to original site of Fred Albert house; 24-29, Belonie Violette's deed on what is now the Val Violette house; These images document a dinner given for elderhostelrs at the University of Maine-Fort Kent; 30, University President Richard Dumont leaves the lectern after some welcoming remarks; 31-32, Musician Paul-Emile Martin sings, accompanying himself on guitar; 33-end, Singer Ida Roy does one of her traditional song.
    - Elderhosteler dinner, University of Maine-Fort Kent, Maine; Anita Albert, weaver, St-Jacques, New Brunswick, Canada; St. Luce Catholic Church, Frenchville, Maine, July 19, 1991 - July 20, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B053; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a dinner held at the University of Maine-Fort Kent; 1-4, Fieldworker and Acadian Archive Director Lisa Ornstein leads a sing-along; 3-4, Don Cyr in his Acadian costume stands at the lectern; 5-6, Visitors from Ste-Ouenne, France, sing several songs, including one written especially for the occasion; The following images document a visit to the home of Anita Albert, a weaver who resides in St-Jacques, New Brunswick; 7-18, Mm. Albert demonstrates her technique to field coordinator Ray Brassieur; 19-22, Mm. Albert works out her patterns on these diagrams; 23-27, Mm. Albert at her loom; 28-29, Mm. Albert demonstrates a device made by her husband Gilbert; FUNCTION?????; A few images of St. Luce Catholic Church, Frenchville, ME; 30-31, This photograph was taken from the hill above St. Luce on Church Road in Frenchville; the hills in the distance are in New Brunswick; 32-end, St. Luce Catholic Church; low contrast conditions make the spire seem to disappear.
    - Buildings and scenes, Upper St. John River Valley area, Maine, July 21, 1991 - July 24, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B054; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes; 2-3, Logging trucks in Frenchville, ME; trucking is an important economic activity in the study area; 4-5, Corriveau buckwheat mill, Frenchville. This mill no longer operates; in fact, there is no currently operating buckwheat mill in the study area; 6-9, Equipment no longer in use at Corriveau Mill; 10-14, Corriveau mill; 15-20, Loons on Eagle Lake, photographed from the deck of the camp occupied by fieldworkers Ray Brassieur and David Whitman; 21-24, Eagle Lake, from the deck of the camp; 25-26, A small herd of cattle on a farm on State Highway 11; 27-28, "Acadia Builders" sign, Fort Kent; the owner of this business is not Acadian, and has recently moved to the area from Massachusetts. He chose this name for his business for its identity value; 29-30, Temporary bridge over the St. John River in Allagash, ME; the former bridge was destroyed in the spring, 1990 flood; 31-32, Farmstead in St. Francis, ME; the barn is an interesting one, and the house has an unusual second-floor gallery; 33-34, Former schoolhouse converted to storage, St. Francis; there were apparently a number of schoolhouses of this style in the area at one time, but all except two have been torn down; 35-36, St. Charles Catholic Church, St. Francis; 36a, St. Paul Congregational Church, St. Francis; this is one of the oldest Protestant churches in the study area. A sign on the church proclaims "First gathered in 1886."
    - Various buildings and scenes and aerial photos, Upper St. John River Valley area, Maine, July 24, 1991 - July 26, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B055; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of buildings; 1-2, Former schoolhouse converted to a part-time residence, St. John, ME. See also MAP-DW-B054, #33-34; 3-4, St. John Catholic Church; there is no priest in residence here, but services are held weekly by a priest from another parish; 5, Presbytery for sale, St. John; 6-7, Former potato house, now home of Northern Maine Tree Farm, Fort Kent; 8-9, A fairly new Protestant church in western Fort Kent; there seems to have been an increase in the number of Protestant churches, especially fundamentalist churches; These images were photographed during an airplane flight over the study area. See ????? and subsequent logs for more information; 10-16, Farmland and forest in the St. John Valley; much of what is now forest was probably once agricultural land. The pattern of fields is suggestive of the original long lot land grants; 17-18, Blank frames; 19-20, Van Buren, ME; 21-22, Village Acadien, Van Buren; the buildings here are said to be arranged in the shape of the letter A; 23-24, Our Lady of Mount Carmel Catholic Church and presbytery, Lille, ME; 25-26, Settlement along the St. John River in New Brunswick; 27-28, This photograph shows line settlement patterns on both the Maine (top) and New Brunswick sides of the river. 29-32 Acadian Cross Historic Shrine, St. David, ME A barn in Eagle Lake; 34-36, This barn is a typical partially buried potato house which, like many, is no longer in use. The sign in front of the barn proclaims "Welcome to Beautiful Eagle Lake."
    - Home of Frances Gendreau, Madawaska, Maine, July 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B056; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a visit to the home of Frances Gendreau in Madawaska, ME; 2-5, Raw croquiqnol dough on the kitchen counter; "croqs" are a traditional fried pastry; 6-7, Cooked croqs; 8-10, Field coordinator Ray Brassieur talks with Frances Gendreau, a schoolteacher and croq-maker extroidinaire; 11-12, Potato barrel canisters on Ms. Gendreau's refrigerator; 13-17, Julie Albert, Ms. Gendreau's mother and a writer on local history, talks about her work; 18-22, After a bit of instruction from Ms. Gendreau, Brassieur tries his hand at making croqs. He fails; 23-25, Ms. Gendreau shows one of her prize kitchen utensils, an old potato knife; 28-30, Stone tool, possibly very old, which Ms, Gendreau got from her Uncle Fred Albert. She believes he dug up a number of such artifacts while plowing his fields; 31-33, Silver snuff box from Fred Albert; 34-end, Small hand-carved wooden box.
    - Frances Gendreau, Madawaska, Maine; St. Agatha Catholic Church, Monfort, Maine; Adrien Morin, potato farmer, Saint David, Maine, July 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B057; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a group of artifacts in the possession of Frances Gendreau of Madawaska; these objects were given to her by her uncle, Fred Albert; 2-3, Small hand-carved wooden box; 4-10, Clay pipe; Ms. Gendreau associates this pipe with a story her uncle told her about smoking it with an American Indian visitor; 11-26, Ms. Gendreau had two stone tools given to her by her uncle; she said that she thought he had unearthed a number of such artifacts while plowing his fields; Some miscellaneous images from St. Agatha, ME; 27-28, St. Agatha Catholic Church; 29-30, Monfort Heights, a former convent converted into a residence facility for senior citizens; 31-32, Plaque on St. Agatha Catholic Church; 33-35, Decorative stonework on St. Agatha Catholic Church; These images document a visit to potato grower and barrel maker Adrien Morin of St. David, ME; 36-end, Morin (front) shows field coordinator Ray Brassieur some of his barrel-making equipment.
    - Visit to home or Adrien Morin, potato grower and barrel maker, Saint David, Maine, July 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B058; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a visit to Adrien Morin, a potato grower and barrel maker in St. David, ME. Wooden potato barrels were once commonly used in the study area when potatoes were harvested by hand, but the advent of mechanical harvesting has rendered them nearly obsolete. Some are still used on area farms for storage; 2-10, Morin shows field coordinator Ray Brassieur how staves are made; 11-12, Adrien's son Ray, who has worked in the barrel making operation, joins the conversation; 13-16, Stave-making equipment; 17-18, The Morins show Brassieur how hoops are made; 19, Material for making wooden hoops; 20-24, Demonstration of hoop-making; 25, Adrien Morin shows how he cuts the bottom of a barrel; 26, Barrel-making equipment; 27, Stacks of barrel bottoms; 29-30, Various parts for the barrel-making equipment; 31-32, One of the buildings which houses part of the barrelmaking operation; 34-36, Ray Morin demonstrates the final assembly process.; 37, Finished potato barrels.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Upper St. John River Valley area, Maine; Eloi Daigle house, Fort Kent, Maine, July 28, 1991 - July 29, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B059; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes; 1-6, Decorative facial boards on the eaves of houses in Wallagrass, ME; there are quite a variety of these throughout the study area, cut in a number of different shapes from triangular to compound-curved examples like these; 7-8, Members of a group calling themselves "Rainbows;" they were traveling from a national gathering of Rainbows in Vermont, and had stopped at this rest area along State Highway 11 in Wallagrass; 9-10, Pump connected to a well at the rest area; 11-12, House in Soldier Pond connected to a former storefront; 13-22, Exterior views of the Eloi Daigle house on U.S. Highway 1 in eastern Fort Kent; this is a typical mid-nineteenth century Acadian house which has been moved and enlarged since its construction. The unpainted sections represent much later additions; 23-30, Closet door in the Eloi Daigle house; an interesting and typically Acadian feature is the chamfered panels on the inside of the door; 31-32, Ship's knee in the Fred Albert house in St. David, ME; 33-36, Close-ups of ship's knee showing the heads of the iron fasteners called drift pins.
    - Various scenes, Madawaska, Maine; Fred Albert House, Madawaska, Maine, June 25, 1991, AFC 1991/029: HM-B001-61317; Howard W. Marshall; 35 35 mm black-and-white film negatives